<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>From the Ground Up - startup</title><link href="n/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="n/feeds/startup.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>n/</id><updated>2017-12-28T04:45:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>One year into a biotech startup: looking back</title><link href="n/one-year-in.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-28T04:45:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-28T04:45:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Katie Planey</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-12-28:n/one-year-in.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the nonlinear path of business model discovery and&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;renewed focus one year into a startup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One year has flown by at Mantra Bio&lt;/strong&gt;.  A little over a year ago, one of my
co-Founders and I were working out of our apartments and just the precious bit of 
personal savings we could give to Mantra Bio.  I had worked just long enough to 
save up a meager PhD salary for one year post-taxes.  Since I had graduated from a PhD
program roughly a year before, I knew I could live off that again. Maybe some day
I\'d be content to actually accrue some personal savings and reap more immediate 
financial rewards of my MBA and PhD degrees.  But I was fortunate to be raised by parents 
that had taken financial risks early in their relationship to be able to provide
my brothers and me with a more than comfortable childhood.  It made for a highly
supportive environment while understanding that you need to take personal risks to 
get personal gains. I had far more resources than my parents had started out with; 
I will be the first to admit that getting a leg up early in life accelerates what 
you can do down the road.  So continuing to live off a strict budget and do some
side consulting if needed (necessary to survive a PhD in the Bay area if you do
not want to live in dorm housing) did not seem a huge risk to me, even though I 
had just turned 30. I had a supportive partner cheering me on, which meant the
world to me.  I was acting more out of a feeling of loyalty and duty to my
parents, and their grandparents, who ran small businesses like truck repair and
dog grooming, and my alma maters of Yale and Stanford, who bestowed on me
unimagineable opportunities. Onward and upward!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;One year in, what is most on my mind is how to truly harness the nonlinear
learnings our team gleaned this past year&lt;/em&gt;.  I keep a company wiki documenting our
technical strategy that I attempt to update every month or so; I think it is
dangergous to view innovation and business/technical strategy as some black box,
when really, it starts with a seed of an idea and grows with twists and turns with
ideas from teammates and external forces. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My co-Founders and I are well-versed in the now-popular concepts of the Lean 
Business Model and Agile Devleopment, both of which emphasize rapid iteration and 
learning. It does no good to write out your business plan in a vacuum and then
blindly follow it (finances aside, your employees are most likely too smart to
know that does not work, either, even if you try and convince them otherwise! They
are the people "on the ground" who can often be the most honest with you about
whether your business model is both feasible and hitting an ideal market.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we did our best to keep our minds, eyes and ears open this past year, and our 
core business and technical strategy did indeed evolve. What I am thinking about
most these days is how to embrace the current iteration of our strategy without
getting too weighed down by all of the hard work and learnings we did last year.
It is a bit akin to an emotional sunk cost. For example, after taking a hard look
at the strategy we all now truly believe is our North Star forward, we realized
that a project we had been dedicating man-hours to on and off was actually pretty
tangential to the core milestones we need to complete in the next two years. This 
project in large part catapaulted us to even start Mantra Bio, so it felt weird to
"retire" it. But with a small team, we cannot be chasing "zombie" projects or
ideas. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first heard the term "zombie" in this respect in a Biodesign class at
Stanford; a serial medical device entrepreneur urged us to hunt down and kill
"zombie" ideas as quickly as possible. This person was not focused on a single
business plan, but rather just wanted to find some sort of medical device that had
legs, but the overall concept stuck with me. Sometimes what kills a project is financial,
sometimes technical, sometimes regulatory, etc.  It does not matter if the idea in
theory sounds great or "sexy". If it does not help you achieve your end strategic
milestones, you need to chuck it quickly.  If it is truly a sunk cost, suck it up
and admit it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deciding on your milestones is a whole separate thread, and of coures this evolves, 
but your team needs to be hyper-focused.  You have to communicate the core, single focus 
and how this focus is achieved through the milestones, in order to empower your
employees to make day-to-day decisions that help the team achieve that core focus.
Otherwise, you will end up with a lot of hard work but deliverables that do not
quite synce together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially critical in biotech;  everyone is an
expert in a different scientific or technical area. It is all hands-on deck and to
make matters more complicated, your team works in physically separate spaces (wet
lab research scientists in the lab and product and data engineers and scientists
in the office). In some ways, you have to act like a bigger company earlier than
say a software company.  You cannot easily switch research projects halfway through 
(even ordering new reagents can slow things down) and
most tasks are not transferrable across team members, so you have to plan and
communicate very carefully, even with a small team. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with a small five-person team, as we enter 2018, our team at Mantra Bio 
is taking care to view the year as a "fresh" slate. We are letting our refined 
busines and technical strategy, honed over this past year, guide exactly what we 
need to achieve, instead of carrying baggage from projects and efforts put forth 
in 2017.  And we condensed that down into a single, one-sentence focus that we
shared with the team before everyone left for the holidays. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not equate to a massive shift at Mantra Bio. Communication of strategic
shifts across the team should be given regularly, in part to allow for feedback. 
And thus the team should mostly nod their heads
when presented a clarified view of the next set of milestones! But we want it to
be crystal-clear to everyone on our team that now, all projects and efforts must
sync up with our singular focus. No one was "off-topic" before, but for us it is
akin to "cleaning house".  And we will re-visit the focus and milestones during
our biweekly sprint reviews, a part of &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/stevedenning/2016/09/08/explaining-agile/"&gt;agile
development&lt;/a&gt;.
We want to focus and cut out the fat, which should also
give teammates more bandwidth to just get sh** done.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="startup"></category><category term="biotech"></category><category term="strategy"></category></entry></feed>